Anupubba-sikkhā

〈 Handa mayaṁ anupubba-sikkha-pāṭhaṁ bhaṇāmase 〉

Taṁ dhammaṁ suṇāti gahapati vā gahapati-putto vā aññatarasmiṁ vā kule paccājāto. So taṁ dhammaṁ sutvā tathāgate saddhaṁ paṭilabhati. So tena saddhā-paṭilābhena samannāgato iti paṭisañcikkhati: Sambādho ghar’āvāso rajopatho abbhokāso pabbajjā. Na’y’idaṁ sukaraṁ agāraṁ ajjhāvasatā ek’anta-paripuṇṇaṁ ek’anta-parisuddhaṁ sankhalikhitaṁ brahmacariyaṁ carituṁ. Yan’nūn’āhaṁ kesamassuṁ ohāretvā kāsāyāni vatthāni acchādetvā agārasmā anagāriyaṁ pabbajeyyanti. So aparena samayena appaṁ vā bhoga-kkhandhaṁ pahāya mahantaṁ vā bhoga-kkhandhaṁ pahāya appaṁ vā ñāti-parivaṭṭaṁ pahāya mahantaṁ vā ñāti-parivaṭṭaṁ pahāya kesamassuṁ ohāretvā kāsāyāni vatthāni acchādetvā agārasmā anagāriyaṁ pabbajati.

[MN 27 / 38 / 51]

Sakkā nu kho bho gotama imasmim’pi dhamma-vinaye evam’eva anupubba-sikkhā anupubba-kiriyā anupubba-paṭipadā paññapetunti?

Sakkā imasmim’pi dhamma-vinaye anupubba-sikkhā anupubba-kiriyā anupubba-paṭipadā paññapetuṁ. Tathāgato purisadammaṁ labhitvā paṭhamaṁ evaṁ vineti: Ehi tvaṁ bhikkhu sīlavā hohi pātimokkha-saṁvara-saṁvuto viharāhi ācāra-gocara-sampanno aṇumattesu vajjesu bhayadassāvī samādāya sikkhassu sikkhāpadesūti.

[MN 107]

So evaṁ pabbajito samāno bhikkhūnaṁ sikkhā-sājīva-samāpanno pāṇ’ātipātaṁ pahāya pāṇ’ātipātā paṭivirato hoti nihitadaṇḍo nihitasattho lajjī day’āpanno sabba-pāṇa-bhūta-hit’ānukampī viharati. Adinn’ādānaṁ pahāya adinn’ādānā paṭivirato hoti dinn’ādāyī dinna-pāṭikankhī athenena sucibhūtena attanā viharati. Abrahmacariyaṁ pahāya brahmacārī hoti ārācārī virato methunā gāmadhammā.

Musāvādaṁ pahāya musāvādā paṭivirato hoti saccavādī saccasandho theto paccayiko avisaṁvādako lokassa. Pisuṇaṁ vācaṁ pahāya pisuṇāya vācāya paṭivirato hoti ito sutvā na amutra akkhātā imesaṁ bhedāya amutra vā sutvā na imesaṁ akkhātā amūsaṁ bhedāya — iti bhinnānaṁ vā sandhātā sahitānaṁ vā anuppadātā samagg’ārāmo samagga-rato samagga-nandī samagga-karaṇiṁ vācaṁ bhāsitā hoti. Pharusaṁ vācaṁ pahāya pharusāya vācāya paṭivirato hoti yā sā vācā n’elā kaṇṇa-sukhā pemanīyā hadayaṅ’gamā porī bahujana-kantā bahujana-manāpā tathā-rūpiṁ vācaṁ bhāsitā hoti. Sampha-ppalāpaṁ pahāya samphappalāpā paṭivirato hoti kāla-vādī bhūta-vādī attha-vādī dhamma-vādī vinaya-vādī nidhānavatiṁ vācaṁ bhāsitā kālena sāpadesaṁ pariyantavatiṁ attha-saṁhitaṁ.

So bījagāma-bhūtagāma-samārambhā paṭivirato hoti ekabhattiko hoti ratt’ūparato virato vikāla-bhojanā nacca-gīta-vādita-visūka-dassanā paṭivirato hoti mālā-gandha-vilepana-dhāraṇa-maṇḍana-vibhūsana-ṭṭhānā paṭivirato hoti uccāsayana-mahāsayanā paṭivirato hoti jātarūpa-rajata-paṭiggahaṇā paṭivirato hoti āmaka-dhañña-paṭiggahaṇā paṭivirato hoti āmaka-maṁsa-paṭiggahaṇā paṭivirato hoti itthi-kumārika-paṭiggahaṇā paṭivirato hoti dāsidāsa-paṭiggahaṇā paṭivirato hoti aj’eḷaka-paṭiggahaṇā paṭivirato hoti kukkuṭa-sūkara-paṭiggahaṇā paṭivirato hoti hatthi-gavassa-vaḷava-paṭiggahaṇā paṭivirato hoti khetta-vatthu-paṭiggahaṇā paṭivirato hoti dūteyya-pahiṇa-gaman’ānuyogā paṭivirato hoti kayavikkayā paṭivirato hoti tulākūṭa-kaṁsakūṭa-mānakūṭā paṭivirato hoti ukkoṭana-vañcana-nikati-sāciyogā paṭivirato hoti chedana-vadha-bandhana viparāmosa-ālopa-sahasākārā paṭivirato hoti.

So santuṭṭho hoti kāya-parihārikena cīvarena kucchi-parihārikena piṇḍapātena. So yena yen’eva pakkamati samādāy’eva pakkamati. Seyyathā’pi nāma pakkhī sakuṇo yena yen’eva ḍeti sapattabhāro’va ḍeti evam’eva bhikkhu santuṭṭho hoti kāya-parihārikena cīvarena kucchiparihārikena piṇḍapātena. So yena yen’eva pakkamati samādāy’eva pakkamati. So iminā ariyena sīla-kkhandhena samannāgato ajjhattaṁ anavajja-sukhaṁ paṭisaṁvedeti.

[MN 51]

Tam’enaṁ tathāgato uttariṁ vineti: Ehi tvaṁ bhikkhu indriyesu gutta-dvāro hohi cakkhunā rūpaṁ disvā mā nimitta-ggāhī hohi m’ānubyañjana-ggāhī. Yatv’ādhikaraṇam’enaṁ cakkhu’ndriyaṁ asaṁvutaṁ viharantaṁ abhijjhā-domanassā pāpakā akusalā dhammā anvāssaveyyuṁ tassa saṁvarāya paṭipajjāhi rakkhāhi cakkhu’ndriyaṁ cakkhu’ndriye saṁvaraṁ āpajjāhi. Sotena saddaṁ sutvā. Ghānena gandhaṁ ghāyitvā. Jivhāya rasaṁ sāyitvā. Kāyena phoṭṭhabbaṁ phusitvā. Manasā dhammaṁ viññāya mā nimitta-ggāhī hohi m’ānubyañjana-ggāhī. Yatv’ādhikaraṇam’enaṁ man’indriyaṁ asaṁvutaṁ viharantaṁ abhijjhā-domanassā pāpakā akusalā dhammā anvāssaveyyuṁ tassa saṁvarāya paṭipajjāhi rakkhāhi man’indriyaṁ man’indriye saṁvaraṁ āpajjāhīti.

Ehi tvaṁ bhikkhu bhojane mattaññū hohi. Paṭisankhā yoniso āhāraṁ āhāreyyāsi n’eva davāya na madāya na maṇḍanāya na vibhūsanāya yāva’d’eva imassa kāyassa ṭhitiyā yāpanāya vihiṁs’ūparatiyā brahmacariy’ānuggahāya iti purāṇañ’ca vedanaṁ paṭihankhāmi navañ’ca vedanaṁ na uppādessāmi yātrā ca me bhavissati anavajjatā ca phāsuvihāro cāti.

Ehi tvaṁ bhikkhu jāgariyaṁ anuyutto viharāhi divasaṁ caṅkamena nisajjāya āvaraṇīyehi dhammehi cittaṁ parisodhehi rattiyā paṭhamaṁ yāmaṁ caṅkamena nisajjāya āvaraṇīyehi dhammehi cittaṁ parisodhehi rattiyā majjhimaṁ yāmaṁ dakkhiṇena passena sīhaseyyaṁ kappeyyāsi pāde pādaṁ accādhāya sato sampajāno uṭṭhāna-saññaṁ manasikaritvā rattiyā pacchimaṁ yāmaṁ paccuṭṭhāya caṅkamena nisajjāya āvaraṇīyehi dhammehi cittaṁ parisodhehīti.

Ehi tvaṁ bhikkhu sati-sampajaññena samannāgato hohi abhikkante paṭikkante sampajāna-kārī ālokite vilokite sampajāna-kārī samiñjite pasārite sampajāna-kārī sanghāṭi-patta-cīvara-dhāraṇe sampajāna-kārī asite pīte khāyite sāyite sampajāna-kārī uccāra-passāva-kamme sampajāna-kārī gate ṭhite nisinne sutte jāgarite bhāsite tuṇhībhāve sampajāna-kārīti.

Ehi tvaṁ bhikkhu vivittaṁ sen’āsanaṁ bhajāhi araññaṁ rukkha-mūlaṁ pabbataṁ kandaraṁ giriguhaṁ susānaṁ vana-patthaṁ abbhokāsaṁ palāla-puñjanti.

So pacchābhattaṁ piṇḍapāta-paṭikkanto nisīdati pallankaṁ ābhujitvā ujuṁ kāyaṁ paṇidhāya parimukhaṁ satiṁ upaṭṭhapetvā. So abhijjhaṁ loke pahāya vigat’ābhijjhena cetasā viharati abhijjhāya cittaṁ parisodheti, byāpāda-padosaṁ pahāya abyāpanna-citto viharati sabba-pāṇa-bhūta-hit’ānukampī byāpāda-padosā cittaṁ parisodheti, thina-middhaṁ pahāya vigata-thina-middho viharati āloka-saññī sato sampajāno thina-middhā cittaṁ parisodheti, uddhacca-kukkuccaṁ pahāya anuddhato viharati ajjhattaṁ vūpasanta-citto uddhacca-kukkuccā cittaṁ parisodheti, vicikicchaṁ pahāya tiṇṇa-vicikiccho viharati akathaṁkathī kusalesu dhammesu vicikicchāya cittaṁ parisodheti.

[MN 107]

Bhikkhu yathā iṇaṁ yathā rogaṁ yathā bandhan’āgāraṁ yathā dāsabyaṁ yathā kantār’addhāna-maggaṁ ime pañca nīvaraṇe appahīne attani samanupassati. Seyyathā’pi bhikkhave āṇaṇyaṁ yathā ārogyaṁ yathā bandhanā-mokkhaṁ yathā bhujissaṁ yathā khemanta-bhūmiṁ evam’eva bhikkhu ime pañca nīvaraṇe pahīne attani samanupassati. So tatonidānaṁ labhetha pāmojjaṁ adhigaccheyya somanassaṁ.

So ime pañca nīvaraṇe pahāya cetaso upakkilese paññāya dubbalī-karaṇe paṭhamaṁ jhānaṁ dutiyaṁ jhānaṁ tatiyaṁ jhānaṁ catutthaṁ jhānaṁ upasampajja viharati.

So evaṁ samāhite citte parisuddhe pariyodāte anangaṇe vigat’ūpakkilese mudu-bhūte kammaniye ṭhite āneñjappatte pubbe-nivās’ānussati-ñāṇāya sattānaṁ cut’ūpapāta-ñāṇāya āsavānaṁ khaya-ñāṇāya cittaṁ abhininnāmeti.

So idaṁ dukkhanti yathā-bhūtaṁ pajānāti ayaṁ dukkha-samudayoti yathā-bhūtaṁ pajānāti ayaṁ dukkha-nirodhoti yathā-bhūtaṁ pajānāti ayaṁ dukkha-nirodha-gāminī paṭipadāti yathā-bhūtaṁ pajānāti.

Ime āsavāti yathā-bhūtaṁ pajānāti ayaṁ āsava-samudayoti yathā-bhūtaṁ pajānāti ayaṁ āsava-nirodhoti yathā-bhūtaṁ pajānāti ayaṁ āsava-nirodha-gāminī paṭipadāti yathā-bhūtaṁ pajānāti.

Tassa evaṁ jānato evaṁ passato kām’āsavā’pi cittaṁ vimuccati bhav’āsavā’pi cittaṁ vimuccati avijj’āsavā’pi cittaṁ vimuccati. Vimuttasmiṁ vimuttam’iti ñāṇaṁ hoti: khīṇā jāti vusitaṁ brahmacariyaṁ kataṁ karaṇīyaṁ n’āparaṁ itthattāyā’ti pajānātīti.

[MN 39]

Ye kho te bhikkhū sekkhā apatta-mānasā anuttaraṁ yoga-kkhemaṁ patthayamānā viharanti tesu me ayaṁ evarūpī anusāsanī hoti.

[MN 107]

Short Blessings of the Entire World

Culla-maṅgala-cakka-vāḷa

〈 Sabba-buddh’ānubhāvena 〉

Sabba-dhamm’ānubhāvena

Sabba-saṅgh’ānubhāvena

Buddha-ratanaṁ dhamma-ratanaṁ saṅgha-ratanaṁ

Tiṇṇaṁ ratanānaṁ ānubhāvena

Catur-āsīti-sahassa-dhamma-kkhandh’ānubhāvena

Piṭakattay’ānubhāvena

Jina-sāvak’ānubhāvena

Sabbe te rogā

Sabbe te bhayā

Sabbe te antarāyā

Sabbe te upaddavā

Sabbe te dunnimittā

Sabbe te avamaṅgalā vinassantu

Āyu-vaḍḍhako

Dhana-vaḍḍhako

Siri-vaḍḍhako

Yasa-vaḍḍhako

Bala-vaḍḍhako

Vaṇṇa-vaḍḍhako

Sukha-vaḍḍhako

Hotu sabbadā

Dukkha-roga-bhayā-verā

Sokā sattu c’upaddavā

Anekā antarāyā’pi

Vinassantu ca tejasā

Jaya-siddhi dhanaṁ lābhaṁ

Sotthi bhāgyaṁ sukhaṁ balaṁ

Siri āyu ca vaṇṇo ca

Bhogaṁ vuḍḍhī ca yasavā

Sata-vassā ca āyū ca

Jīva-siddhī bhavantu te

With all the power of the Buddha, all the power of the Dhamma, all the power of the Saṅgha. The gem of the Buddha, Dhamma, Saṅgha. The power of the Triple Gem. The power of the 84,000 Dhamma aggregates, the power of the Tipitaka, the power of the Victor’s disciples: May all your diseases, all your fears, all your obstacles all your dangers, all your bad visions, all your bad omens be destroyed. May there always be an increase of life, wealth, glory, status, strength, beauty and happiness. May suffering, disease, fear, animosity, sorrow, adversity, misfortune, and various obstacles vanish through this power. Triumph, success, wealth, gain, safety, luck, happiness, strength, glory, long life, beauty, fortune, growth, status, lifespan of 100. Success in your livelihood: May they be yours!

[MJG]

Purpose and Benefits of Dhamma Recitation

Historical Background

After finding the path to Nibbāna and some initial hesitation, the Buddha eventually decided to teach the Dhamma (MN 26). His first disciples were a group of five monks, and with the awakening of one of them, Ven. Kondañña, the wheel of Dhamma was set in motion (SN 56.11). While these first disciples were taught exclusively by the Buddha himself, soon afterwards more monks reached the final goal. Subsequently, the Buddha sent out the first sixty arahants to teach the Dhamma (SN 4.5, Vin I 20).

During that period of ancient India, religious texts were not commonly written down. Even for the purpose of ordinary education, most learning occurred through memorization. Writing was known but not used for religious texts which were considered too sacred to be put into writing; instead they were meant to live in the minds and hearts of those who saw their value, and made the effort to memorize them. In particular, the Brahmins were known for their proficiency in committing their corpus of sacred texts (Vedas) to memory and maintaining them with astonishing accuracy. Part of their skill can be attributed to the fact that memorization started from a young age. Likewise, also in Buddhist literature we can discover clear traces of standardization and mnemonic tools to ensure accuracy and to make memorization easier. In particular, the use of recurring stock phrases makes it easier to commit a large corpus of texts to memory (Anālayo, 2019). There is not much known about the specific teachings shared with their audience by the first arahants who went out to teach the Dhamma. But it is fair to assume that they took some teachings with them that were brief and easy to memorize. Let us also keep in mind that the Buddha’s disciples were not trained in memorization from childhood, but they came from all walks of life – young, old, educated, uneducated etc. Only when the Saṅgha had grown in size, monks who specialized in recitation travelled all across India and shared the Buddha’s teachings with those eager to hear them (Analayo, 2007).

A passage that illustrates the Buddha’s own appreciation of recitation stems from a conversation he had with a monk who had gone forth just recently. Without warning, the Buddha asked him to recite the Dhamma. The newly ordained monk recited the Aṭṭhakavagga of Sutta Nipāta (Ud 5.6). The Buddha was pleased and complimented the monk on his skills in remembering, keeping in mind, articulating, and enunciating the texts. This highlights the Buddha’s emphasis that recitation of the Dhamma was meant to be taken seriously by his ordained disciples.

The Workings of Memory

Contrary to our intuition, memory doesn’t function like a scanner or copying machine that takes a snapshot of a text or event, and saves it for later. Instead, anecdotal memory works in a relational manner. The brain links new information that comes in through any of the six senses to concepts based on memories from the past. We understand new things in the light of and from the perspective of, things we already know. Likewise, we remember old things through the filters and biases of the present moment. It is so natural for us to draw inferences that we are often unaware that we are doing so (Eysenck, 1992/2005). This interplay between past and present gives our memory great potential due to its seemingly unlimited storage capacity (the Buddha recollected past lifetimes from memory, counting back many eons of world-dissolution and evolution). At the same time the interplay between past and future also makes memory inherently unreliable. The importance of memorization becomes clear. When texts are memorized literally, personal interpretation, biases, and coloring by past experiences and present circumstances have less opportunity to distort the information. Accuracy increases further if one checks the memorized text from time to time against its original, either by looking it up in a book, or by reciting it together with others. In this way, differences become apparent straight away.

Benefits for Dhamma Practice

In the discourses the Buddha is often depicted taking up the topic of recitation when explaining to monks the proper way to learn the teachings, and to make these teachings the vessel within which their own wisdom can grow.

He has learned much, remembers what he has learned, and accumulates what he has learned. Those teachings that are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, with the right meaning and phrasing, which proclaim the perfectly complete and pure spiritual life—such teachings as these he has learned much of, retained in mind, recited verbally, mentally investigated, and penetrated well by view. This is the fifth cause and condition that leads to obtaining the wisdom fundamental to the spiritual life. (AN 8.2)

In our current age of easy access to Dhamma books and multimedia, it is tempting to conclude that it is now not necessary anymore to memorize large bodies of texts for the sake of transmission, and that we are blessed with being able to read any of the texts at any time, from the comfort of our kuṭis or living rooms. And blessed we are. Nonetheless, even today recitation has benefits that surpass a regular silent reading, or even reading out loud. As seen in the earlier quote from AN 8.2, the Buddha doesn’t only speak about reciting the texts verbally, but also about retaining them in mind and investigating them mentally. This is where the benefits of recitation differ considerably from a more casual reading, or even from chanting with the help of a chanting book. By means of committing a text to memory, it lives much deeper within our minds and hearts, and we can reflect on it whenever and wherever we choose. Dhamma that has been well-memorized, is always with us. The Buddha’s teachings become accessible in the very moment we need them, without having to resort to a book or an e-reader.

Since right view is the first of the eight path factors, it is of great importance for progress on the path to keep the Buddha’s teachings in mind so that they can shape our views and perspectives. By keeping them actively in memory one can recognize their relevance whenever a situation in life occurs when they naturally manifest, or when they are most necessary to intentionally recall. Recollecting the Dhamma can be a source of joy, leading to rapture, tranquility, and concentration (AN 5.26); factors that can lead to a pleasant abiding here and now. It can also help to abandon drowsiness (AN 7.61), as well as speed up recovery from illness (AN 46.16), or to achieve a stage of awakening even on the deathbed (AN 6.56). In fact, reciting the Dhamma is one of the occasions that can even bring about the attainment of final liberation (AN 5.26).

Though the bhikkhu Phagguṇa’s mind had not yet been liberated from the five lower fetters, when he heard that discourse on the Dhamma, his mind was liberated from them… There are, Ānanda, these six benefits of listening to the Dhamma at the proper time The Vinaya defines the wrong time for eating as from noon until dawnrise of the following day. and of examining the meaning at the proper time. What six?

...At the time of his death he does not get to see the Tathāgata or a disciple of the Tathāgata, but he ponders, examines, and mentally inspects the Dhamma as he has heard it and learned it. As he does so, his mind is liberated in the unsurpassed extinction of the acquisitions. This is the sixth benefit of examining the meaning at the proper time. (AN 6.56)

In whatever way the bhikkhu recites the Dhamma in detail as he has heard it and learned it, in just that way, in relation to that Dhamma, he experiences inspiration in the meaning and inspiration in the Dhamma. As he does so, joy arises in him. When he is joyful, rapture arises. For one with a rapturous mind, the body becomes tranquil. One tranquil in body feels pleasure. For one feeling pleasure, the mind becomes concentrated. This is the third basis of liberation, by means of which, if a bhikkhu dwells heedful, ardent, and resolute, his unliberated mind is liberated, his undestroyed taints are utterly destroyed, and he reaches the as-yet-unreached unsurpassed security from bondage. (AN 5.26)

Benefits for Rebirth

The depth to which a mere reading of a text penetrates the mind is incomparable to the depth of penetration that can be reached by memorization. AN 4.191 depicts monks who have memorized the Dhamma, and are subsequently reborn in circumstances with little to no exposure to the Dhamma. The sutta explains that not only in the current lifetime, but also in lifetimes ahead, the Dhamma that was previously memorized will be accessible and has a chance of being re-cognized or recollected even in a future existence, e.g. as a deva. With the support of sufficient samādhi, not only can the Dhamma be recollected, but even one’s past lives:

Bhikkhus, ...there are things to be realized by memory… And what are the things to be realized by memory? One’s past abodes are to be realized by memory. (AN 4.189)

Benefits for Communal Life

Besides being of benefit to one’s own Dhamma practice, and the benefits during future lifetimes, reciting the Dhamma can also have a beneficial impact on communal life. Accounts of the Buddhist councils (saṅgīti; lit. recitations) show that in all these important events of Buddhist history when the extended Saṅgha family came together, the DhammaVinaya was recited together, as a means to remain aligned with the teachings and to foster harmony. Another feature of monastic communities, is the fortnightly recitation of the Pātimokkha, the rules for monks and nuns, in which even solitary forest dwellers, including Arahants, were encouraged by the Buddha to participate, as they made their way to the nearest monastery in the vicinity (Mv.II.5.5). Recitation of texts together not only strengthens a common commitment to the DhammaVinaya, but in a more practical way, it also enables monastics to chant in sync and unison when reciting together with their spiritual companions. This not only increases clarity and understanding, but also makes for a more homogenous listening experience at a ceremony, e.g. a dāna or bereavement service conducted by monastics. Furthermore, the coming together frequently to recite the Buddha’s teachings creates a bond among Saṅgha members and leads to their growth. This would not be so if everyone recited the Dhamma on his own.

And what, bhikkhus, are the seven principles of non-decline? (1) As long as the bhikkhus assemble often and hold frequent assemblies, only growth is to be expected for them, not decline. (2) As long as the bhikkhus assemble in harmony, adjourn in harmony, and conduct the affairs of the Saṅgha in harmony, only growth is to be expected for them, not decline. (AN 7.23)

Recitation Among Monastics

While it is not uncommon in our current time and age that teachers share the Dhamma without any reference to the Buddha or his teachings, in the Buddha’s time the teachings were passed on from teacher to disciple by means of recitation. The Vinaya texts explain that if the preceptor wants one to recite [C: memorize passages of Dhamma or Vinaya], one should recite. If he wants to interrogate one [C: on the meaning of the passages], one should answer his interrogation. (Cv.VIII.12.2-11)

BMC I mentions that the Vibhaṅga to Pācittiya 4 lists four ways in which a person might be trained to be a reciter of a text:

The teacher and student recite in unison, i.e. beginning together and ending together.
The teacher begins a line, the student joins in, and they end together.
The teacher recites the beginning syllable of a line together with the student, who then completes it alone.
The teacher recites one line, and the student recites the next line alone.

In order for a monk to be free from dependence (nissaya) on a teacher, he must be learned and intelligent, knowing both Pāṭimokkhas... and must have been ordained as a bhikkhu for at least five years (Mv.I.53.5-13).

The Commentary says that a learned bhikkhu must have memorized:

Both Pātimokkhas (for the bhikkhus and bhikkhunīs).
The Four Bhāṇavāras — a set of auspicious chants that are still regularly memorized in Sri Lanka as the Mahā-pirit poṭha.
A discourse that is helpful as a guide for sermon-giving.
Three kinds of anumodanā (rejoicing in the merit of others) chants: for meals; for auspicious merit-making ceremonies, such as blessing a house; and for non-auspicious ceremonies, i.e. any relating to a death.

Lastly, when monastics from other sects wanted to become monks in the Buddha’s dispensation, they typically had to undergo a four-month probation period. However, a probationer fails in his probation and is not to be accepted... if he does not have a keen desire for recitation (Mv.I.38.5-10).

Once again, we can see the immense emphasis that was placed on memorization and recitation, starting already during the Buddha’s own ministry, and continuing all the way to the 21st century, where we can still find monks who are able to memorize the entirety of the Tipiṭaka.

What to Recite

While recitation and memorization of the Dhamma yields several benefits, and one may be committed to dedicate some amount of time to this worthwhile endeavor, one important task remains. Given the limited amount of texts one may be able to memorize and maintain in memory, the task is: the selection of texts for recitation and memorization, there being such a vast amount of teachings that the Buddha left behind. What is essential - what is secondary? Once again, we are in the fortunate situation that the Buddha himself gave guidance in what he regarded as the core teachings. In MN 104 the Buddha points to a set of 37 teachings, commonly known as the Wings of Awakening (bodhipakkhiyā dhammā). Included in these 37 Dhammas are the four foundations of mindfulness, the four right strivings, the four bases of spiritual power, the five faculties, the five powers, the seven factors of awakening, and the noble eightfold path. (DN 16). Other teachings that are commonly held in high esteem are the The Discourse on Setting in Motion the Wheel of Dhamma (Dhammacakkappavattana-sutta), The Gradual Training, and The Dhamma in Brief. All of these are teachings that can help the earnest practitioner to gain an overview of the Dhamma and one’s path to liberation. Practicing accordingly, further recollection and recitation of such teachings also helps to correctly assess one’s own progress on the path.

Besides these general teachings, the Buddha also went into great depth in explaining the most profound doctrines, some of which are related to the conceptual framework surrounding the practice, while others are directly related to formal meditation. Early sermons that stand out in this context are The Discourse on the Characteristic of Not-Self (Anatta-lakkhaṇa-sutta), The Discourse on the Exposition on Burning (Āditta-pariyāya-sutta), the Buddha’s First and Final Words, Mindfulness of Breathing, and Dependent Origination. All of these are profound, deep teachings that highlight key aspects of the path to awakening. These are teachings that are good to memorize and recite again and again (AN 10.48), allowing their deep meaning to gradually seep into our hearts.

From these profound teachings we can take a step back to the practical, day-to-day perceptions that the Buddha specifically recommended to be frequently reflected upon. In this category we find The Five and The Ten Subjects for Frequent Reflection, also the reflections on The Four Requisites, and a separate reflection on The Repulsiveness of Food. Recollection of Impermanence, The Three Characteristics, and The Thirty-Two Parts are also frequently mentioned in the discourses. Perceptions that are closely related to the second path factor of the noble eightfold path, i.e. right thought (sammā saṇkappa), are the Metta Sutta and The Divine Abidings. Perceptions that arouse the four Brahmavihāras can seamlessly lead the practitioner towards the eighth path factor, sammā samādhi. At times when energy is lacking, however, chants that inspire, motivate, or arouse urgency, can be used to heat up and revitalize the practice. This is where Striving According to the Dhamma, The Burdens, Respect for the Dhamma, and the Miscellaneous Verses can come to the rescue.

Lastly, this recitation book also includes passages that illuminate how to establish good relations among fellow practitioners, such as the Principles of Cordiality, Principles of Non-Decline, and The Four Great References. Also included are chants that monks commonly perform as services to the laity, such as Anumodanā, Sharing of Merits, and Funeral Chants.

To summarize, memorization of the Dhamma and group recitation fulfill a variety of different purposes and benefits, ranging all the way from the mundane aspects such as the ability to recite in unison and the fostering of communal harmony, all the way to the attainment of final liberation.

When to Recite

The chants within this book have been arranged thematically in such a way (see the Recitation Schedule), that they can be recited on a rotation basis over a period of 10 days. Each set/day can be recited in approximately 35 to 40 minutes, depending on the fluency and speed of the reciter or chanting leader.

How to Recite

See chapter Pāli Phonetics and Pronunciation in the Appendix.

References

Anālayo, Bhikkhu 2007: Oral Dimensions of Pāli Discourses: Periscopes, other Mnemonic Techniques and the Oral Performance Context, Canadian Journal of Buddhist Studies, 3: 5-33.

Analayo, Bhikkhu 2019: Ancient Indian Education and Mindfulness, Springer Science+Business Media

Eysenck, M. W. et al. 1992/2005 Cognitive Psychology, Hove: Psychology Press.

DeGraff, Geoffrey (Ṭhānissaro Bhikkhu) 2013: The Buddhist Monastic Code II, Valley Center, CA: Metta Forest Monastery

The Refuges and Trainings

Undertaking the Three Refuges^158

(Repeat each phrase after the leader)

Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammāsambuddhassa [3x]

Homage to the Blessed, Worthy, and Perfectly Enlightened One.

Buddhaṁ saraṇaṁ gacchāmi

Dhammaṁ saraṇaṁ gacchāmi

Saṅghaṁ saraṇaṁ gacchāmi

To the Buddha I go for refuge.

To the Dhamma I go for refuge.

To the Saṅgha I go for refuge.

Dutiyam’pi buddhaṁ saraṇaṁ gacchāmi

Dutiyam’pi dhammaṁ saraṇaṁ gacchāmi

Dutiyam’pi saṅghaṁ saraṇaṁ gacchāmi

For the second time, to the Buddha I go for refuge.

For the second time, to the Dhamma I go for refuge.

For the second time, to the Saṅgha I go for refuge.

Tatiyam’pi buddhaṁ saraṇaṁ gacchāmi

Tatiyam’pi dhammaṁ saraṇaṁ gacchāmi

Tatiyam’pi saṅghaṁ saraṇaṁ gacchāmi

For the third time, to the Buddha I go for refuge.

For the third time, to the Dhamma I go for refuge.

For the third time, to the Saṅgha I go for refuge.

〈 Tisaraṇa-gamanaṁ niṭṭhitaṁ 〉

〈 This completes the going to the Three Refuges. 〉

Āma bhante

Yes, venerable sir.

Endnotes

^1 Due to the balanced and inspiring selection of chants, as well as for the sake of compatibility, WPN Buddhist Chanting (2014) has served as the basis for this book. Over time, suggestions for the inclusion of additional chants, as well as occasional improvements of existing translations were incorporated. Such changes were meticulously marked down in the endnotes, so that someone familiar with the present book can straight away find the relevant differences, which can be useful when visiting a branch monastery of the Ajahn Chah lineage, in order to know in which places to revert to the original version.

^2 WPN: The Lord. The underlying Pāli term is Arahant. Lord, however, has connotations that do not fit well to the way the Buddha is portrayed in the discourses. In dictionaries lord is commonly defined as: an appellation for a person or deity who has authority, control, or power over others, acting like a master, a chief, or a ruler. The Worthy One seems a better choice of terms, since it is also how Arahant was used in pre-Buddhist era. PTS explains:[Vedic arhant, ppr. of arhati (see arahati), meaning deserving, worthy]. Throughout this chanting book, all occurrences of Arahant have therefore been consistently translated as Worthy One, thus replacing previous translations, such as The Lord, Noble One etc.

^3 WPN: He trains perfectly those who wish to be trained. The aspect of wishing to be trained is not found in the Pāli.

^4 WPN: He has explained the spiritual life of complete purity. While spiritual life is not a bad translation, for the sake of consistency with the rest of the chanting book, this occurrence was changed to holy life.

^5 To practice directly(Pāli: uju) means, to practice the most direct way to Nibbāna; the straight way; no detours.

^6 WPN: Who have practiced insightfully

^7 WPN: Those who practice with integrity

^8 WPN: They give occasion for incomparable goodness to arise in the world

^9 WPN: The teaching of the Lord like a lamp

^10 WPN: Illuminating the path and its fruit, the Deathless

^11 WPN: That which is beyond the conditioned world

^12 WPN: To that which is worthy. This passage refers to the triple (taya) gems and not just to the Saṅgha.

^13 One who knows things as they are is an unusual translation for Tathāgata. Also arisen in is better than has come into, otherwise one might think that he has come from somewhere, already being a Tathāgata.

^14 No mention of delusion in the Pāli. It could also refer to samsāra or dukkha.

^15 WPN: grief

^16 WPN: In brief the five focuses of identity are dukkha

^17 WPN: Attachment to mental formations. While the Pāli term saṅkhārā only means formations, Bhikkhu Bodhi’s rendering as volitional formations captures well the intentional/volitional forces behind the formative nature of the mind.

^18 WPN: Attachment to sense-consciousness

^19 WPN: Mental formations are impermanent

^20 WPN: Sense-consciousness is impermanent

^21 WPN: Mental formations are not-self

^22 WPN: Sense-consciousness is not-self

^23 WPN: All conditions are transient

^24 WPN: There is no self in the created or the uncreated. While this is not a very accurate translation, it is indeed the case that the term sabbe dhammā includes the uncreated, Nibbāna (see AN 5.32).

^25 WPN: All of us are bound by birth ageing and death

^26 WPN: grief

^27 In Pāli, these terms are in plural form, however, for the sake of recitation they are kept singular.

^28 WPN: All of us are bound by birth ageing and death

^29 WPN: Being fully equipped with the bhikkhus’system of training

^30 WPN: what not: ‘What not’ is usually followed by what is similar. Furthermore, the meaning of adhamma in this context describes not only the lack of Dhamma, but the practice of wrong Dhamma.

^31 WPN: lack of Dhamma This translation is problematic, because a mere lack of Dhamma does not lead to rebirth in hell; otherwise all non-Buddhists would be destined to hell. In reality, it is the view and practice of wrong Dhamma that leads to hell, which is also substantiated by the Commentary, which defines adhamma as the opposite (paṭipakkha) of true Dhamma.

^32 This line is missing in WPN.

^33 WPN: from suffering

^34 WPN: Whoever goes to refuge

^35 WPN: In the Triple Gem. It has been shown in Āyasma Aggacitta’s Do We Go to the Triple Gem for Refuge? that one does not go for refuge in the triple gem (the Buddha, Dhamma, and Ariya-saṅgha), but the discourses repeatedly depict the Buddha, Dhamma, and Bhikkhu-saṅgha as the community to take refuge in (DN 2, MN 91, SN 12.46, AN 2.16 etc.).

^36 There are two variations as to the sequence of these three verses. The sequence used here follows the sequence of Dhp 183 (Sabba pāpassa...), Dhp 184 (Khantī paramaṁ...), Dhp 185 (Anūpavādo...). In contrast, the sequence Dhp 184, 183, 185 is commonly known as the Ovādapātimokkha, and occurs at DN 14.

^37 WPN: Impermanent are all conditioned things

^38 Dukkha here refers to the five aggregates themselves, as explained in SN 56.11: The five aggregates of clinging are dukkha. Along similar lines, the five aggregates are called burdens in SN 22.22.

^39 WPN: Dukkha are all conditioned things

^40 WPN: From the floods dry land they reach

^41 WPN: Living withdrawn so hard to do

^42 WPN: The beast of burden though is man. The Pāli word puggalo is in masculine, which is the expected grammatical form even if a term refers to males and females alike, as is probably the case here. Furthermore, the phrase beast of burden is an English idiomatic expression, signifying an animal used for heavy work such as carrying or pulling things (Oxford Dictionary).

^43 Unity here refers to unity of mind due to concentration (samādhi, cittass-ekaggatā). Nekatta = na + ekatta [abstr. fr. eka].

^44 WPN: The dust of passions all the more. The Pāli only speaks of stirring up dust, but the Commentary explains that it refers to the dust of kilesā. As a translation for kilesā, the term defilements has a broader scope than just passions, wherefore the former has been given preference.

^45 The meaning of this statement is somewhat cryptic. The Commentary explains as follows: pamādo rajo = heedlessness is dust; pamādo pamād’ānupatito rajo = the dust that follows heedlessness is (also) heedlessness; the Commentary further explains that this is about procrastination, e.g. I am still young, so I can afford to be heedless; maybe later I’ll be heedful.

^46 WPN: viddhā. The Siam edition has viddhā (pierced) whereas the Burmese and Sri Lankan edition of the same text have vidvā (the wise), which seems to be the variant that better conveys the intended meaning of the text.

^47 WPN: Such insight is one’s strength

^48 WPN: Thus for a night of non-decline

^49 WPN: a shining night of prosperty

^50 The term blessing is used throughout this chanting book to convey the meaning of support, or a beneficial thing, without implying the underlying Christian connotations this term may have in popular use.

^51 WPN: Was staying at Sāvatthī

^52 WPN: that harm no being

^53 WPN: And hearing the Dhamma frequently taught

^54 WPN: And sharing often the words of Dhamma

^55 WPN: ardent committed

^56 WPN: Even

^57 What is translated here as cherishing all living beings, could more literally be translated as developing a measureless mind towards all beings.

^58 WPN: to fixed views. This paragraph deals with Anāgāmis, which becomes apparent from the closing statement in which it is said that by this practice one becomes free from sense desires and is not born again into this world (sense sphere). The limitation of loving-kindness practice leading only up to Anāgāmihood also finds confirmation by AN 4.126. Now, since an Anāgāmi has right view, which is the first factor of the noble eightfold path (even Arahants hold right view; AN 10.112), it would therefore not be correct to say that he holds no views at all. Furthermore, even an Anāgāmi may still have some minor grasping to (right) view, as there can still be moments of māna (identification/conceit), which is overcome only by the Arahant. I therefore conclude that this passage here refers specifically to wrong views and does not include right view, since wrong views are the only types of views that an Anāgāmi has entirely left behind.

^59 WPN: It is this Noble Eightfold Path

^60 For some reason byādhi’pi dukkho is missing from the WPN version of this chanting book. The reason for this omission is unclear, because even the Thai edition of this discourse contains byādhi’pi dukkho. However, the definition of the four noble truths in the context of the Satipaṭṭhānasuttas in DN and MN do not contain byādhi’pi dukkho. It may be that the compilers of this chanting book copy/pasted this passage from the wrong discourse, thinking it is the same, whereas in reality there is this small difference.

^61 WPN: grief

^62 WPN: In brief the five focuses of identity are dukkha

^63 WPN: Light arose

^64 WPN: Now this Noble Truth of dukkha

^65 WPN: As long bhikkhus as

^66 The three phases are comprised of the statement of the noble truth itself, followed by what is the task that is to be performed in relation to this noble truth, followed by the statement that the task has been performed. Four truths multiplied by three phases, results in 12 aspects.

^67 Instead of the nominative abhisambuddo (Thai and Buddha Jayanti Pāli edition), one would usually expect the accusative or a quotation here, which is indeed what is found in the PTS and Chatta Saṅgāyana editions, giving abhisambuddho’ti. However, the anoumolous reading abhisambuddho finds support from Mahāvasutu: yāvac cāhaṁ bhikṣavaḥ imāni catvāry āryasatyāni evaṁ triparivartaṁ dvādaśākāraṁ yathā-bhūtaṁ samyakprajñayā nābhyajñāsiṣaṁ na tāvad ahaṁ anuttarāṁ samyaksaṁbodhim abhisaṁbuddho pratijānehaṁ, which according to Ven. Ānandajoti probably indicates that abhisambuddho is an old/original reading.

^68 WPN: But when bhikkhus

^69 Bhikkhu Bodhi: [those people]. Removed brackets for the sake of recitability.

^70 The Vinaya defines the wrong time for eating as from noon until dawnrise of the following day.

^71 Contrary to popular belief, mindfulness and full awareness is not meant to be practiced while sleeping, but only before falling asleep and after waking up.

^72 WPN: covetousness

^73 Descriptions of right and wrong livelihood can be found at AN 5.83, AN 5.177, AN 6.18, AN 8.54, AN 10.91.

^74 WPN: covetousness and grief

^75 WPN: He abides contemplating mind-objects as mind-objects. Since mind-object is not an ideal translation for dhamma in this context, it is preferable to leave dhamma untranslated here.

^76 Quite secluded from sense pleasures means being completely and entirely secluded; not just somewhat/moderately secluded. The Pāli term eva, which has been translated as quite is an emphatic particle, intensifying the adjective it qualifies. According to the Oxford English Dictionary, the English term quite has two connotations: 1. to the utmost – or most – absolute extent or degree; absolutely; completely; 2. To a certain or fairly significant extent or degree; fairly. It is the first connotation in which quite is used in the phrase quite secluded from sense pleasures.

^77 The meaning of pasāda as confidence also finds expression in the qualities of a stream-enterer, who is declared to have aveccapasāda (AN 3.75) in the Buddha, Dhamma, and Saṅgha, which Āyasmā (Bhikkhu) Bodhi translates as unwavering confidence and Āyasmā (Bhikkhu) Sujāto translates as experiential confidence. The qualifier ajjhatta as found in the stock formula of the second Jhāna is rendered as inner/self confidence. Alternative translations for ajjhattaṁ sampasādanaṁ would be inner serenity, inner clarity, inner joy, and it is up to the reader/reciter to reflect on these additional connotations of the term as seen fit.

^78 WPN: Still feeling pleasure with the body. The Pāli doesn’t say still, but more importantly SN 48.40 states that physical pleasure (sukha) has ceased in third Jhāna, and mental pleasure (somanassa) has ceased in fourth Jhāna. Therefore, according to SN 48.40 kāya in the context of the third Jhāna stock formula cannot refer to the physical body. The Pāli commentaries agree, and explain that kāya here refers to the mental body, in particular to mental pleasure (somanassa). However, a comparative study by Prof. Kuan Tse-Fu titled Clarification on Feelings in Buddhist Dhyāna/Jhāna Meditation brought to light that the Chinese parallel to SN 48.40 has a different sequence of disappearing types of vedanā in the sequence of the four Jhānas. While it would go beyond the scope of this footnote to discuss the matter in detail, it is noteworthy that the parallel to SN 48.40, the Aviparātaka Sūtra of the Āgamas, indeed mentions that bodily pleasant feeling (sukha) disappears only in the fourth Jhāna, whereas mental pleasant feeling (somanassa) has disappeared already in the third Jhāna, alongside with the disappearance of pīti. In the context of this chanting book, we have therefore chosen to stay with the literal translation of the word kāya as body, and invite the reader to draw his own conclusions.

^79 WPN: viharatī’ti

^80 WPN: grief

^81 WPN: I shall breathe in tranquillising the bodily formations. Kāyasaṅkhāraṁ is singular, not plural.

^82 WPN: I shall breathe in experiencing the mental formation. Cittasaṅkhāraṁ is probably meant to be singular, not plural, but this is not always clear when looking at compounds. Considering that the subsequent practice explicitly uses mental formation in singular, this suggests that it is probably used in the same way here.

^83 WPN: I shall breathe in tranquillising the mental formation. Cittasaṅkhāraṁ is singular, not plural.

^84 While virāga indeed can refer to the mind’s fading away of passions (dispassion), in certain contexts virāga refers to fading away of any phenomena. One such instance can be found in MN 74: Pleasant/unpleasant/neutral feeling, Aggivessana, is impermanent, conditioned, dependently arisen, subject to destruction, vanishing, fading away, and ceasing. Here, virāga obviously does not refer to mental dispassion, but to the nature of fading away of certain phenomena i.e. feeling. Likewise, in the context of mindfulness of breathing, virāga can be seen as part of the natural progression of the lifecycle of any phenomena, including but not limited to the breath itself, which after its arising, goes through a phase of change (aniccā), gradual fading (virāga), and ending in its cessation (nirodha). The meditator observing these stages develops an attitude of letting go (paṭinissagga) towards it, because there is nothing that is worth clinging/adhering to (MN 37).

^85 This chant stems mainly from The Discourse Analysis of Dependent Origination, a sub-chapter from the The Analysis of Dependent Origination, which is part of the second book of the Abhidhammapiṭaka called the Vibhaṅga (Abh.Vibh.130f). Apart from minor variations, there is great similarity between this analysis and the analysis found in SN 12.2, in Suttapiṭaka. The first four lines of this chant stem from SN 12.61, which functions as an illustration of the general principle of conditionality.

^86 Here and at other places of the English translation, the term a condition is used. The indefinite article a indicates that there could be other conditions as well (e.g. all previous conditions in the sequence are a condition for all subsequent ones), but the directly aforementioned condition is the predominant one (adhipati-paccaya) for the subsequent conditioned thing to arise.

^87 Here and at other places of the English translation, the term arises is inserted, because the term sambhavati from Jāti-paccayā jarā-maraṇaṁ; soka-parideva-dukkha-domanass’upāyāsā sambhavanti applies to all 11 links (12 minus ignorance) and not only to ageing-and-death etc.

^88 Elsewhere in the chanting book the term saṅkhāra is translated as volitional formations. Here, however, for the sake of ease of recitability in subsequent passages within this chant, it is translated as formations.

^89 In the context of dependent origination, the compound nāma-rūpa is translated as mind-and-body in order to cover the entirety of what is conventionally called a being, a person. In other contexts, particularly if used separately, these terms may have other connotations.

^90 Here and at other places of the English translation, the term arises is inserted, because the term sambhavati from Jāti-paccayā jarā-maraṇaṁ; soka-parideva-dukkha-domanass’upāyāsā sambhavanti applies to all 11 links (12 minus ignorance) and not only to ageing-and-death etc.

^91 To render as Therein what is from ignorance as a condition arise formations would be misleading, because it is not the conditioned relationship between A and B (here: ignorance and formations) that gets elaborated upon in the following lines, but it is only the term B (here: formations), that gets defined. Hence the preferable translation: Therein what are ‘formations’, arising from ignorance as a condition?

^92 SN 12.51 explains: Bhikkhus, if a person immersed in ignorance generates a meritorious volitional formation, consciousness fares on to the meritorious; if he generates a demeritorious volitional formation, consciousness fares on to the demeritorious; if he generates an imperturbable volitional formation, consciousness fares on to the imperturbable.

^93 While the Pāli term mayā literally means made of/constructed by, it wouldn’t be correct to take this passage to mean that giving, virtue, and meditation are the causes for wholesome volition. Rather, the wholeosme volition leads to and expresses itself through giving, virtue, and meditation. Or in the words of Dhp 2: Phenomena are preceded by the mind, surpassed by the mind, created by the mind. If one speaks or acts with a pure mind - happiness follows; just as one’s shadow that never leaves.

^94 Further explained in SN 12.25.

^95 Manosañcetanā citta-saṅkhāro is translated here as volition associated with the mind is the mental formation. Despite mano and citta having different shades of meaning in certain contexts, both were translated here as mind. Generally speaking mano refers more to the intellectual, whereas citta covers more the emotional/affective aspects of the mind. A detailed analysis of these terms can be found in Rune E. A. Johansson’s Citta, Mano, Viññāṇa — a Psychosemantic Investigation.

^96 While Vibh 130 introduces a new definition for nāma as vedanā-kkhandho, saññā-kkhandho, saṅkhāra-kkhandho, this definition stands in tension with the discourses, where nāma is consistently defined as vedanā, saññā, cetanā, phassa, manasikāra (e.g. MN 9, SN 12.2). It is for this reason that the passage from Vibh 130 was replaced with the fivefold nāma as found throughout the suttas.

^97 The term vāda in attavādupādāna does here not necessarily refer to a doctrine of self, but rather to a person’s sense of being someone; the sense of being or having a self. This is not exactly the same as personality view, which is destroyed already at the stage of stream-entry. The lingering sense of having a self may continue for a while, despite having already intellectually and/or experientially understood that there is no self to be found in relation to the five aggregates; just as conceit (māna) is overcome only by the path to Arahantship, despite having uprooted personality view already at the stage of stream-entry.

^98 Here the Vibh. differs substantially from the analysis found in the suttas. It introduces a distinction between action becoming (kammabhava) and rebirth becoming (upapattibhava). Kammabhava is taken to refer to wholesome, unwholesome and imperturbable actions; upapattibhava is taken to refer to sense/form/formless-sphere becoming, percipient/non-percipient/neither-percipient-nor-non-percipient becoming, one/four/five-component becoming. But since AN 3.76 says that kamma (together with consciousness and craving) is a condition for bhava (if no kamma...then no becoming in the sense-sphere etc. would be discerned), it is not fit to say that kamma itself is a form of bhava (kammabhava). However, it would go too far for the purpose of this chanting book, to discuss further implications of the analysis found in Vibh. For the sake of simplicity and emphasis on the earliest strata of the Buddha’s teachings, we substituted the passage from Vibh. with the passage from SN 12.2, which defines becoming (bhava) simply as sense/form/formless-sphere becoming. Understood in this way, becoming (bhava) functions as an intermediary between clinging and birth, highlighting the gradual process of how rebirth in one of the three planes of existence takes place. This can even include an interim period between death and birth; thus it is called becoming, rather than instant birth straight after death.

^99 While SN 12.2 does not contain a full elaboration on all types of dukkha, a similar analysis is found in DN 22.

^100 While SN 12.2 does not contain an elaboration on the different types of misfortune (vyasana), it is found in DN 33, AN 4.192, and AN 5.130. Diṭṭhi here does not mean just any view, but right view. The loss of other views would not be particularly unfortunate from a Buddhist perspective, especially the loss of wrong view could be regarded as a great blessing. The right view that is lost in this example is not the right view of a noble disciple, but the right view of a worldling (puthujjana), whose right view is not unshakeable and who may or may not change his view later on throughout the course of the present life or subsequent births.

^101 Anglicising of Pāli words is quite arbitrary. For masc. and neuter we use the stem, but for fem. we use the nominative, wherefore Gotami (voc.) becomes Gotamī.

^102 In Girimānandasutta (AN 10.60) the Buddha instruced Ven. Ānanda: If, Ānanda, you visit the (severely sick) bhikkhu Girimānanda and speak to him about ten perceptions, it is possible that on hearing about them his affliction will immediately subside. Then the same seven perceptions as above are mentioned, with the addition of the following three: 8. the perception of non-delight in the entire world; 9. the perception of impermanence in all conditioned phenomena, and 10. mindfulness of breathing. Girimānandasutta concludes: Then, when the Venerable Ānanda had learned these ten perceptions from the Blessed One, he went to the Venerable Girimānanda and spoke to him about them. When the Venerable Girimānanda heard about these ten perceptions, his affliction immediately subsided.

^103 WPN: By human strength/energy/effort; while purisa can also mean person, or human, in this context it probably refers to the feature of strength, which is typically associated with masculinity. A similar analogy occurs with the expression of a strong man (purisa) extending or contracting his arm (AN 7.61).

^104 WPN: omitted evil (pāpa) in its translation.

^105 WPN: like the cream of the milk; maṇḍapeyya is a Pāli idiom, meaning of the best quality (lit. to be drunk like cream)

^106 WPN: avaññā

^107 WPN: thinking in such a way: our going forth will not be barren

^108 WPN: And supports for the sick

^109 WPN: sampādetun

^110 WPN: Change is the nature of conditioned things

^111 In the original version, this line is followed by When they act upon intention, which is not found in the Pāli, and is potentially misleading, giving the implication that intention alone is not enough to count as kamma.

^112 WPN: All beings are the owners of their action and inherit its results. Their future is born from such action, companion to such action, and its results will be their home. All actions with intention, be they skilful or harmful, of such acts they will be the heirs. For the sake of consistency with other chants within this chanting book, the original version was replaced with the one found in the Five Subjects for Frequent Reflection, and Ten Subjects for Frequent Reflection.

^113 The compound sabbattatāya (sabba-t-tatāya) seems to be an extension of its predecessor sabbadhi (everywhere), and could thus even more suitably be translated as spreading to the entire (world); tata: extended; spread out. (pp. of tanoti).

^114 WPN: a heart imbued with gladness

^115 WPN: For good or for ill, of that I will be the heir. For the sake of consistency with other passages which were translated differently, that translation has been chosen.

^116 WPN: recollect

^117 WPN: Bhikkhus there are ten dhammas

^118 WPN: I am no longer living according to worldly aims and values

^119 WPN: I should strive to abandon my former habits

^120 WPN: For good or for ill, Of that I will be the heir For the sake of consistency with other passages which were translated differently, this translation has been chosen.

^121 WPN: bowels

^122 WPN: entrails

^123 In the discourses, except for one occasion in the Khp, the brain is not mentioned as a separate organ or body part, making it a list of only 31 body parts.

^124 WPN: Everything is void of self

^125 WPN: Completely void of use

^126 WPN: Their nature is to rise and fall

^127The following passage is absent in the Thai edition of the Tipiṭaka: Bhikkhavoti; Bhadanteti te bhikkhū bhagavato paccassosuṁ. Bhagavā etad’avoca.

^128 The entire original version of the English translation has been replaced.

^129 The following passage is absent in the Thai edition of the Tipiṭaka: ‘Bhikkhus’ – ‘Venerable sir’, they replied. The Blessed One said this:

^130 Ariyasāvaka can be translated as noble disciple or disciple of the noble one (ariyassa+sāvaka=ariyasāvaka). I have opted for the first option here because the discourse addresses the group of five monks who all were Ariyas already at that time, but it needs to be kept in mind that the term ariyasāvaka does not always refer to individuals who have already attained one of the four paths or fruits. This can be seen from MN 27, where a person is referred to as ariyasāvaka without reference to any form of awakening-attainment. It is only at the end of the discourse that this ariyasāvaka attains awakening.

^131 The word the teaching is not explicitly expressed in the Pāḷi, but was inserted for comprehension.

^132 Kataṁ karaṇīyaṁ, n’āparaṁ itthattāyā’ti literally means What has to be done is done. There is nothing else (to so) for the sake of such a (liberated) state. For a discussion of this passage see Bhikkhu Bodhi, Middle Length Discourses, Bhayabheravasutta, MN 4, footnote 76.

^133 The entire original version of the English translation has been replaced.

^134 WPN: So will what’s here been given

^135 WPN: Bring blessings to departed spirits

^136 When chanted for laypeople, the first part of this chant, until here, is recited only by the Saṅghatthera.

^137 When chanted for laypeople, this line is recited only by the secondmost senior monk. Afterwards, the remainder of the Saṅgha joins in.

^138 When chanted for laypeople, the first part of this chant, until here, is recited only by the Saṅghatthera.

^139 This line is recited only by the secondmost senior monk. Afterwards, the remainder of the Saṅgha joins in.

^140 In the Thai tradition, a long pause is made after sukhaṁ, and balaṁ is recited in a slow and drawn-out manner.

^141 For translations of the above see the the previous chant, titled Just as Rivers Full of Water.

^142 The first four lines were composed by Āyasmā Aggacitta, functioning as an introduction to the chant.

^143 WPN: paṭībhāna-do

^144 The Invitation to the Devas is traditionally performed as a solo introduction by the thirdmost senior monk. However, any monk who has been invited by the Saṅghatthera can do so.

^145 When chanted for laypeople, only the second line (Dhamma-ssavana kālo...) is recited, which is repeated three times.

^146 WPN: Payirūpāsana. Pari + upa = payirupa

^147 WPN: Osathaṁ. Osatha is not a word found in Pāli dictionaries, but osadha (medicine) is. The spelling osatha is due to a faulty transliteration, influenced by Thai style of Pāli pronunciation, where d often becomes t. The Mahā-jaya-maṅgala-gāthā was originally composed in Sri Lanka. The Sri Lankan version indeed speaks of osadha, thus confirming above explanation for the spelling error.

^148 WPN: devānumodantu

^149 Here and in all subsequent verses we find the word jitavā. The standard spelling would be jitvā (abs. of jināti; having conquered). In contrast jitavā is a transliteration based on Thai spelling and pronunciation of Pāli, which has a tendency to insert the letter a between two consonants such as -tvā, thus making it into -tavā. It is by spelling anomalies like this, that Pāli scholars can determine the place of origin and age of certain Pāli texts.

^150 WPN: paṇidhi and padakkhiṇā

^151 While these faculties are mentioned as a set of 22 only in the Abhi. Vibh., all of them are also found within the discourses.

^152 WPN: Their nature is to rise and fall

^153 While the celestial bodies themselves are not regarded as living beings, this passage refers to the similarly named young devas (candimā/sūriyo devaputto) residing there. See also SN 2.9-10. Furthermore, the term rājā (leaders/kings) does not refer to guṅavantā (virtuous people), but to suriyo candima (sun and moon). A translation closer to the meaning of the Pāli would be: The sovereign Sun and Moon, and also virtuous people.

^154 This probably refers to 1. worldly or human happiness; 2. celestial or heavenly happiness; 3. transcendent happiness or Nibbāna. Rhys Davids Pāli-English Dictionary - sukha: Two kinds, viz kāyika & cetasika; at Pts.i.188; several other pairs at AN.i.80; three (praise, wealth, heaven) Iti.67; another three (manussa°, dibba°, Nibbāna°) Dhp-a.iii.51; four (possessing, making good use of possessions, having no debts, living a blameless life) AN.ii.69

^155 The Pāli speaks about Māra’s forces.

^156 Even though a Paccekabuddha does not (or is not able to) teach the path to Nibbāna, he can nonetheless give guidance in good conduct and virtue; functioning as an inspirational role model.

^157 Darkness and delusion is not a literal translation for Māra.

^158 The Thai tradition recites Ahaṁ bhante tisaraṇena saha pañca/aṭṭha sīlāni yācāmi three times which translates to I, venerable sir, request the Three Refuges and the Five/Eight Precepts before Namo tassa...

^159 WPN: precept. The same applies to the next four lines.

^160 WPN: drugs which lead to carelessness

^161 WPN: which

^162 WPN: at inappropriate times

^163 WPN: entertainment, beautification, and adornment

^164 WPN: These are the Eight Precepts; Virtue is the source of happiness, Virtue is the source of true wealth, Virtue is the source of peacefulness. Therefore let virtue be purified